经过数年，我们发现DES和3DES明显不是为
Over the years it became clear that DES
and triple DES are simply not designed for
现代硬件设计的，它们速度太慢了
于是NIST启动了一个新的项目
modern hardware and are too slow. As a
result, NIST started a new process to
标准化了一个新的分组密码叫做高级加密标准
standardize in a new block cypher called
the Advanced Encryption Standard or AES
简称AES。NIST最初于1997年请求立项
for short. NIST started it's effort in 1997
when it requested, proposals for a new
寻找新的分组密码。一年后它收到了15个提交方案
block cipher. It received fifteen
submissions a year later. And finally in
最终在2000年，它采取了Rijndael密码
the year 2000, it adopted the cypher
called Rijndael as the advanced encryption
作为高级加密标准。这是一个在比利时设计的密码
standard. This was a cypher designed in
Belgium. We already said that it's block
之前说过，它的分组大小是128位，有三种可能的
密钥大小：128位、192位和256位
size is 128 bits and it has three possible
key sizes. 128 bits, 192, and 256. Now,
使用的密钥越长，分组密码的安全性越高
the assumption is that the larger the key
size is, the more secure the block cipher
作为一个伪随机置换而言。但因为
在操作中有更多的回合数
is as a pseudo random permutation. But
because it also has more rounds involved
密码变得更慢了。所以密钥越长
in its operation. The slower the cipher
becomes. So the larger the key supposedly,
密码越安全，但是会变慢。比如说
the more secure the cipher, but also the
slower it becomes. So for example, AES 128
AES128位是这三个密码中最快的。AES256是最慢的
is the fastest of these ciphers and AES
256 is the slowest. Now AES is built as
AES是基于代换置换网络构建的，并Feistel网络
what's called a substitution permutation
network. It's not a Feistel network.
记住在Feistel网络里，每回合一半的位是不变的
Remember that in a Feistel network, half
the bits were unchanged from round to
在代换置换网络中，每回合所有位都会变
round. In a substitution permutation
network all the bits are changed in every
这个代换置换网络是这样的，这里是它的第一回合
round. And the network works as follows,
so here we have the first round of the
首先我们用回合密钥异或当前状态
substitution permutation network, where
the first thing we do is we XOR the
这里用第一个回合密钥
current state with the round key. In this
case the first round key. Then we go thru
然后我们经过一层代换，分组被其他分组替代
a substitution layer, where blocks of data
are replaced with other blocks based on
替代过程由代换表指定。然后我们经历了一个置换层
what the substitution table says. And then
we go through a permutation layer where
各位被置换移位。然后我们再做一遍
bits are permuted and shuffled around. And
then we do this again. We XOR with an X
我们用相应回合的回合密钥进行异或
然后经历一个代换过程，然后置换各位
round key, we go thru a substitution
phase, and we're permute to dance around.
等等。直到我们到达最后的回合
And so on, and so on, and so forth. Until
we reach the final round where we XOR
我们用最后的回合密钥进行异或，得到输出
with the very last round key, and then
outcomes the output. Now, an important
现在，这个设计的一个要点是，如所设计的
point about this design. Is that, in fact,
because of how it's built, every step in
这个网络的每一步都可逆，所以整个过程都是可逆的
this network needs to be reversible, so
that the whole thing is reversible. And so
所以我们可以解密，我们根据输出
the way we would, decrypt, essentially, is
we would take the output and simply apply
以相反的方向应用网络里的每一步
那么我们从置换的步骤开始
each step of the network in reverse order.
So we start with the permutation step, and
确保这一步是可逆的
we have to make sure that step is
reversible. Then we look at the
然后再看代换层，也确保这一层是可逆的
substitution layer, and we have to make
sure this step is reversible. And this is
这和DES非常不同，记得DES代换表
very different from DES. In DES, if you
remember, the substitution tables were not
(DES代换表就是S盒子)
完全是不可逆的。事实上，它们将6位映射到4位
reversible at all. In fact, they
map six bits to four bits. Whereas
而这里的一切都是可逆的，否则无法解密
here, everything has to be reversible,
otherwise it would be impossible to
当然和回合密钥异或也是可逆的，对吧？
decrypt. And of course the XOR with the
round key is reversible as well. Okay? So
那么代换置换网络的逆就是简单地
inversion of a substitution permutation
network is simply done by applying all of
从相反方向应用各步。现在我们理解了这个通用模型
the steps in the reverse order. So now
that we understand the generic
让我们看看AES的具体步骤。AES密钥128位
construction. Lets look at the specifics
of AES. So AES operates on a 128 bit block.
也就是16个字节。我们写16个字节
Which is sixteen bytes. So what we do with
AES is we write those sixteen bytes as a
写成4x4的矩阵，其中每一项包含一个字节
four by four matrix. Each cell in the
matrix contains one byte. And then we
我们从第一回合开始。我们用第一回合的密钥异或
start with the first round. So we XOR
with the first round key and then apply a
然后应用一个特定的函数，包括代换和置换
certain function. That, includes
substitutions and permutations and other
以及对当前状态应用的其他操作
这里的三个函数也必须是可逆的
operations on the state. And again, these
three functions that are applied here have
这样密码才能被解密
to be invertible so that in fact the
cypher can be decrypted. And then we XOR
然后我们和下一个回合密钥异或，再做一次
with the next round key and we do that
again. Again we apply the round function
我们再次应用回合函数和异或回合密钥
我们一次又一次地这样做
and XOR the round key. And we do that
again and again and again. We do it ten
我们做上10次。尽管很有意思的是，
在最后一轮里没有MixColumn操作
times. Although interestingly in the last
round, the mix column step is actually
最后，我们和最后一回合的密钥异或，得到输出
missing. And then finally, we XOR with the
last round key, and outcomes the output.
这里的每一步，都有这个4x4矩阵
Again, in every phase here, we always,
always, always keep this four by four
输出也总是4乘4，即16个字节，128位
array. And so the output is also four by
four, which is sixteen bytes, which is 128
这些长密钥本身当然是来自16字节的AES密钥
bits. Now the long key themselves of
course come from a sixteen byte AES key
使用密钥扩张而得。那么密钥扩张将一个16字节AES密钥
using key expansion. So the key expansion
maps from a sixteen bytes AES key
映射到11个密钥，每一个密钥都是16字节
into eleven keys, each one being sixteen
bytes. So these keys themselves are also a
所以这些密钥本身也都是4x4矩阵，与当前状态异或
four by four array that's XORed into the
current state. Okay, so that's the
好，这就是AES的工作原理。现在唯一剩下的是
schematic of how AES works. And the only
thing that's left to do is specify these
指定这里的三个函数：ByteSub, ShiftRow和
MixColumn。这些是容易解释的
three functions, byte sub, shift row, and
mix column. And those are fairly easy to
我从高层次为大家描述一下
explain. So I'm just gonna give you the
high level description of what they are.
大家可以上网查找相关细节
And, those interested in the details can
look it up online. So the way byte
字节代换ByteSub是一个包含256个字节的S盒子
substitution works, is literally it's one
S box containing 256 bytes. And
对当前状态里的每一个字节应用S盒子
essentially, what it does is it applies
the S box to every byte in the current
让我解释一下什么意思。当前状态是个4乘4表
states. So, let me explain what I mean by
that. So the current state is gonna be
我们有这个4乘4表
this four by four table. So here we have
the four by four table. And to each
对表中的每一项，我们使用S盒子。我们称之为A表
element in this table, we apply the S box.
So let's call it the A table. And then
然后对所有4乘4个项，我们有下一步
what we do is, essentially, for all four
by four entries, essentially, the next
Aij成为了查找表中对应的项
step, Aij becomes the current step
evaluated at the look up table. So we use
那么我们使用当前值作为查找表的索引
the current cell as an entry, as an index,
into the look up table. And then the value
然后输出查找表里的值。好，这是第一步
of the look up table is what's output.
Okay. So, that's the first step. The next
下一步是ShiftRow，就是一个置换
step that happens is a shift row step,
which is basically just a permutation. So
我们对每一行的四个字节像移火柴一样移动
essentially we kind of do a stick lick
shift on each one of the rows. So you can
大家可以看到第二行被平移了一位
see the second row is stick lick shifted
by one position. This third row is
第三行被平移了两位，而第四行
stick lick shifted by two positions and
the third row is stick lick shifted by
(口误：third->fourth)
被平移了三位。我们要做的最后一件事是
MixColumn，我们应用
three positions. And the last thing we do
is mix columns where literally we apply a
一个线性变换，对每一列进行变换
linear transformation to each one of these
columns. So there's a certain matrix that
将一特定的矩阵乘以每一列的向量，得到新的列
multiplies each one of these columns and
it becomes, the next column. So these
这些线性变换被独立地应用在各个列上
linear transformation is applied
independently to each one of the columns.
现在我应该指出，目前ShiftRow和MixColumn
Now, I should point out that, so far,
shift rows and mixed columns are very easy
是非常容易用代码实现的。我应该说字节代换
to implement in code. And I should say
that the byte substitution itself is
是容易计算的，这样大家可以写出代码
also easily computable, so that you can
actually write code that takes less than
代码长度可以少于256个字节，你可以精简AES的表述
256 bytes to write. And you can kind of
shrink the description of AES by literally
通过使用代码来计算这个代替表，
而不是直接把表的内容硬写在代码里
storing code that computes the table
rather than hardwiring the table into your
事实上这是个关于AES的普遍事实
implementation. And in fact, this is kind
of a generic fact about AES, that if you
如果你不允许预先计算的话，包括即时计算S盒子
can have allowed no pre computation at
all, including computing the S box on the
那么其实你获得的AES实现也还挺小
fly. Then in fact you get a fairly small
implementation of AES, so it, it could fit
对于非常受限的硬件环境AES也可以适应
比如存储复杂代码的空间不够
on very constrained environments where
there isn't enough room to hold,
当然，这是最慢的实现
complicated code. But of course, this will
be the slowest implementation, because
因为一切都是即时计算的，因此这个实现
everything is computed now on the fly, and
as a result, the implementation,
显然比预先计算好的要慢
obviously, is gonna be, slower than things
that were pre-computed. And then there is
这是个代偿。比如说如果你的空间够大
可以存储大量代码
this trade off. For example if you have a
lot of space, and you can support large
你可以预先计算这三步的结果
code. You can actually precompute quite a
bit of the three steps that I just
我刚才说了，事实上，有多种预计算方法
mentioned. In fact, there are multiple
options of pre-computation, you can build
你可以建立一个只有4K字节大小的代换表
你可以建更长的表
a table that's only four kilobyte big. You
can build a table that is even longer,
可以是24K字节的。实现中你会有这些很大的表
maybe 24 kilobytes. So basically you will
have these big tables in your
然后实现的实际性能是很好的
implementation. But then your actual
performance is going to be really good,
因为你所做的只有查找表和异或
because all your doing is just table
look-ups and XORs. You're not doing
不会做复杂的数值计算。因此可以做很多
any other complicated arithmetic. And as a
result, if you can do a lot of
预计算，包括这里三步
pre-computation, these three steps here,
ByteSub, ShiftRows and mix
ByteSub, ShiftRows和MixColumn可以被
转化成很小的查找表
columns can be converted just into a
number, a small number of table lookups
和异或操作。只需计算S盒子
and some XORs. All you can do is
just compute the S box, so now your
现在实现就只有256字节了，硬性编码的
implementation would just have 256 bytes.
Hard coded. The rest would just be code
剩下来的代码计算这三个函数
that's actually computing these three
functions. The performance would be slower
性能会比前面的步骤差一点，但代码规模更小
than in the previous step but the code
footprint would also be smaller. So in
总的来说，代码大小和性能之间有一个很好的平衡点
overall, there's this nice tradeoff
between code size and performance. So on
在高端机器、服务器上，你可以承担大量代码
high-end machines, on high-end servers,
where you can afford to have a lot of
就可以预先计算，把这些大表存到代码里
以获得最好的性能
code, you can precompute and store these
big tables and get the best performance.
而在低端机上，比如8位智能卡或
Whereas on low-end machines like eight
bit smart cards or think of like an eight
8位腕表，你就可以有一个较小的AES实现
bit wristwatch, you would actually have a
relatively small implementation of AES.
当然其速度不会那么快。这有个例子不太寻常
But as a result of course it won't be so
fast. So here's an example that's a little
假设你想用Javascript实现AES
unusual, suppose you wanted to implement
AES in Javascript so you can send an AES
将AES库发给浏览器，这样浏览器就可以自己用AES了
library to the browser and have the
browser actually do AES by itself. So in
这时你就既要减少代码大小
this case what you'd like to, to is you'd
like to both shrink the code size, so that
使得发送给浏览器的网络传输的流量最小
on the network there's minimum traffic to
send a library over to the browser but, at
同时，又要让浏览器的性能尽可能地快
the same time, you'd like the browser
performance to be as fast as possible. And
那么这就是我们刚才所做的
so this is something that we did a while
ago essentially the idea is that the code
想法是发送给浏览器的代码不含任何预先计算好的表
that actually gets send to the browser
doesn't have any pre computer table and as
代码体积较小。但当代码到达浏览器时
a result is fairly small code. But then
the minute it lands on the browser, what
浏览器会预先计算所有的表
the browser will do is actually pre
compute all the tables. So in some sense
某种意义上代码体积不大，很紧凑
the code goes from just being small and
compact. It gets bloated with all these
预计算表使代码体积膨胀。不过表可以存在电脑上
一般笔记本电脑内存够大
precomputed tables. But those are stored
on the laptop, which presumably has a lot
一旦你有了预计算好的表，就可以用它们来加密了
of memory. And then once you have the
precomputed tables you actually encrypt
这就是如何取得最好的性能，对吧？
using them. And that's how you get the
best performance. Okay? So if you have to
所以如果一定要在网络上去实现AES，
不同情况下最佳解决方案是不同的
stand in implementation AES over the
network, you can kind of get the best of
网络上传输的代码不大，但当它到达客户端时
all worlds. Whereas, the code over the
network is small, but when it reaches the
它可以自我膨胀，以获得最佳性能
target client, it can kind of inflate
itself. And then get the best performance
因为在客户端上进行加密的。现在AES是很流行的密码
as it's doing encryption on the clients.
Now AES is such a popular block cipher,
可以为需要加密的产品构建密码
now essentially when you build crypto into
products essentially your supposed to be
因此Intel可以让处理器支持AES
using AES, and as a result Intel actually
put AES support into the processor itself.
由于Westmere有特殊的Intel处理器指令
So since Westmere there are special
instructions in the Intel processor to
用来加速AES。我把这些指令列在这里了
help accelerate AES. And so I listed these
instructions here. They come in two pairs,
他们成对出现，aesenc和aesenclast，
还有aesekygenassist
aesenc and aesenclast. And then, there's aesekygenassist. So, let me explain
认为解释一下它们是干什么的
aesenc实现了AES的一轮加密
what they do. So, aesenc essentially
implements one round of AES. Namely, apply
用回合密钥和明文异或，再应用三个函数
the three functions in the XOR with the
round key. And aesenclast basically
aesenclast实现了AES的最后一回合
implements the last round of AES.
Remember, the last round didn't have the
最后一回合不含MixColumn，只有ByteSub
和ShiftRows
mix columns phase. It only had the subs
bytes and shift rows. And so that's what
这就是aesenclast所做的。这些指令
the aesenclast does. And the way you
call these instructions is using 128 byte
使用128字节的寄存器，对应AES的状态
registers which correspond to the states
of AES. And so you would have one register
会有一个寄存器包含状态值，另一个寄存器
包含当前回合密钥
containing the states and one register
containing the current round key. And then
当你调用AES时，使用这两寄存器，运行一回合的AES
when you call AES on these two registers,
basically, they would run one round of AES
然后把结果存到这个XMM里面的一个状态寄存器
and place the result inside of this XMM
one state register. And as a result if you
因此如果你想实现整个AES，你需要调用aesenc九次
wanted to implement the whole AES. All you
would do is, call aesenc nine times. Then
然后你调用aesenclast一次，这10条指令
you would call aesenclast one time. These
ten instructions are basically the entire
就是整个AES的实现了。就这么多
在这个硬件上容易实现AES
implementation of AES. That's it. It's that
easy to implement AES on this hardware
由于这些操作是在处理器内部做的
and they claim because these operations
are now done inside the processor not
不是处理器实现的外部指令
using external instructions that are
implemented in the processor. They claim
设计者声称可以获得14倍的加速
that they can get a fourteen X speedup
over say an implementation that's running
相比不用特殊指令实现AES的同等条件的硬件
in the same hardware but implementing AES without these special instructions. So
这是一个重要的加速。事实上，目前有很多产品
this is quite a significant speed up and
the facts are now lots of products that
使用了这些特殊指令。我们说这并非Intel的特例
make use of these special instructions.
And let's just say that this is not
AMD也有类似的指令实现
specific to Intel, if you're in
AMD, and they also implemented
在他们的bulldozer结构里
exactly kinda similar instructions in
their bulldozer architecture and further
以及今后的体系结构里。好
我们来讨论AES的安全性
and future architectures. Okay, so let's
talk about the security of AES. I wanna
我想说两种根据。显然，AES被研究很多了
mention just two attacks here. Obviously,
AES has been studied quite a bit. But the
但这两是仅有的针对整个AES的攻击
only two attacks on the full AES are the
following two. So, first of all, if you
首先，如果你想还原密钥，目前最好的攻击
wanted to do key recovery, the best
attack, basically, is only four times
只比穷举攻击快4倍。这意味着不是128位
faster than exhaustive search. Which means
that instead of 128 bits
你真正需要考虑的AES密钥只有126位
然后进行穷举
key, really you should be thinking of AES
is 126 bit key. Cause exhaustive search,
确实比穷举快4倍。当然，126位
really it's gonna four times faster than
it should. Of course due to the 126, it's
依然超过了我们能计算的范围
这并不会伤害AES的安全性
still more time than we have to compute,
and this really does not hurt the security
更重要的攻击则是针对AES256的
alias. The more significant attack is,
actually, on AES-256. It turns out there's a
实际上AES256的密钥扩张的设计上有弱点
weakness in the key expansion design of
aes which allows for, what's called a
会导致相关密钥攻击
什么是相关密钥攻击？
related key attack. So, what's a related
key attack? Essentially, if you give me
如果给我大约2的100次方个AES的输入输出对
但是是由4个相关联的密钥得来的
about two to the 100 input output pairs
for AES, but from four related keys. So,
这些密钥之间关系密切，比如密钥一
these are keys that are very closely
related, namely key number one is just
只比密钥二相差一位，密钥二和密钥三
也只有一位不同
one bit flip of key number two, which is just
one flip, bit flip of key No. three, which is
密钥三和密钥四也只有一位不同
这些是关系非常紧密的密钥
just one flip bit flip of key No. four. These
are very closely related keys, if you like
如果你密钥间的Hamming距离非常短
但如果要实施根据的话
your Hamming distances very short. But
if you do that, then, in fact, there is a
(Hamming距离：相异位数)
有2的100次方次攻击。应该说，2的100次方依然不现实
two to the 100 attack. Now you should say,
well, two to the 100 is still impractical.
这并不是我们今天实际能跑的。不过
This is still more time than we can
actually run today. But nevertheless, the
事实上它比穷举攻击好太多了
fact that it's so much better than an
exhaustive search attack, it's so much
比2的256次方好太多了。这是AES的一个局限性
better than two to the 256. It's kind of a
limitation of the cipher. But generally,
但总的来说它不算是很重要的局限，因为
它需要紧密关联的密钥
it's not a significant limitation, because
it requires related keys. And so, in
实际上，如果你是随机选择密钥的
practice, of course, you're supposed to be
choosing your keys at random, so that you
你的系统里没有关联密钥，那么这个攻击将不适用
have no related keys in your system. And
as a result, this attack wouldn't apply.
但如果你有关联密钥，就会有问题了
But if you do have related keys, then
there's a problem. So this is the end of
本节完结。下一节我们讨论更多
the segment, and in the next segment we're
gonna talk about more provably secure
可证明是安全的分组密码
constructions for block ciphers.